Guide to the Nels F. S. Ferré Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Nels F. S. Ferré Papers
1940-1968
RG 286
Yale University Divinity School Library
7
(11 boxes)
The collection documents the professional life of Nels F. S. Ferre, who was professor of Christian Theology at Andover Newton Theological School (then known as Andover Theological Seminary - 1939-1950,1957-1965), at Vanderbilt University, and at the College of Wooster.
Ferré, Nels F. S. (Nels Frederick Solomon), 1908-1971
Biographical / Historical
Nels F.S. Ferre was born in Sweden in 1908, and came to the United States at the age of 13. He received his undergraduate degree from Boston University in 1931. His interest in philosophy and theology led him to pursue the B.D. degree at Andover Newton; he graduated with the class of 1934. He received the AM. and Ph.D. degrees from Harvard University in 1936 and 1938 respectively. His doctoral work included a year of study at the universities of Uppsala and Lund. He was ordained to the Congregational ministry in 1934.
It was as a teacher and writer that Ferre made his major contributions to American thought. Academic appointments included the following: Instructor in Philosophy (1937-1939) and Abbot Professor of Christian Theology (1939-1950, 1957-1965), Andover Theological Seminary (now Andover Newton Theological School); Professor Philosophical Theology (1950-1957), Vanderbilt University; Scholar in Residence (1965-1968), Parsons College; Ferris Professor of Philosophy (1968-1971), College of Wooster. In addition, he was visiting professor at several institutions and offered many lectureship series.
Ferre's publications include the following books: Swedish Contributions to Modern Theology (1939), The Christian Fellowship (1940), The Christian Faith, An Inquiry into its Adequacy as Man's Ultimate Religion (1942), Return to Christianity (1943), Faith and Reason (1946), Evil and the Christian Faith (1947), Pillars of Faith (1948), Christianity and Society (1950), The Christian Understanding of God (1951), Strengthening the Spiritual Life (1951), The Sun and the Umbrella (1953), Christian Faith and Higher Education (1954), Making Religion Real (1955), Christ and the Christian (1958), Know Your Faith (1959), Searchlights on Contemporary Theology (1961), God's New Age (1962), The Finality of Faith (1963), Reason in Religion (1963), A Theology for Christian Prayer (1963), The Living God of Nowhere and Nothing (1966), A Theology for Christian Education (1967), and The Universal Word (1969).
Nels Ferre died in Wooster, Ohio, in 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School Collection, 2017
Scope and Contents
The Nels F. S. Ferre Papers, 1940-1968, document his professional work. The collection is arranged according to the following categories: diaries, date/address books, lecture notes, unpublished literary manuscripts, notes on readings, and collected articles and dissertations written about Ferre.
Refer to faculty publication register for itemization of Ferre's publications.
Arrangement
Series I. Diaries and address books Series II. Lecture Notes Series III. Unpublished Literary Manuscripts Series IV. Notes on Readings Series V. Material about Ferré
Ferré, Nels F. S. (Nels Frederick Solomon), 1908-1971; Andover Newton Theological School
- Diaries and Date/Address Books, Series I
  - Diaries, 1940, 1942, 1945, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Date/address books, 1944, 1945, 1947 (2), 1951, 1952, 1951-52, 1953, 1954, 1955, 1956, 1957, 1958, 1959, 1960, 1961, 1963, 1964, 1965 (2), 1966, 1967 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Series II
  - John to Ferré (NFSF), 1953 June 26 (Box 1)
  - Gustaf Wingren to NFSF (in Swedish), 1958 September 9 (Box 1)
  - Paul Tillich to NFSF, 1960 September 19 (Box 1)
  - Gustaf Aulen to NFSF (in Swedish), 1963 April 2 (Box 1)
  - George P. Chandler to NFSF, 1968 June 26 (Box 1)
  - NFSF to Wayne (regarding resignation from Parsons College), 1968 (Box 1)
- Notes, Series III
  - Lecture notes, College of Wooster, Phil339, Whitehead Contemp., 1969 (Box 1)
  - Personal library holdings (undated lists) (Box 2)
- Unpublished Literary Manuscripts, Series IV
  - A Charge to Danforth Teachers (Box 2)
  - The Christian Basis for Family Life (Box 2)
  - The Christian in Business (Box 2)
  - A Christian Pilgrimage (Prayer Service), 1944 (Box 2)
  - The Explanatory Word (seven chapters) (Box 2)
  - The Fabric of Paul Tillich's Theology (Box 2)
  - Hope by Stereotype (Box 2)
  - Learning and Life (Box 2)
  - The Place of Philosophy in the Curriculum (Box 2)
  - Relation of the Church to the War in the Light of the Christian Faith, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Theology and the Modern Student (Box 2)
  - Theses on the Freedom of the Will, for the D Society, Cambridge University (Box 2)
- Notes on Readings, Series V
  Scope and Contents
  This material consists of typed or handwritten notes and quotations on 3x5 and 4x6 index cards. The first part consists of cards as organized by NFSF, both by author and by topic. The second part consists of cards which had not been organized by NFSF; these are now organized into uncategorized notes and an alphabetical organization of authors quoted.
  - Notes on Authors (organized by NFSF): Adams-St. Simon (Box 3)
  - Notes on Authors (organized by NFSF): Smith, N.K.-Yuase (Box 4)
  - Notes on Topics (organized by NFSF): Art-Holy Spirit (Box 4)
  - Notes on Topics (organized by NFSF): Incarnation-XIV:Catalogue of Reality, Love (Box 5)
  - Uncategorized Notes - Quotations: (arranged alphabetically by author) A (Box 6)
  - Uncategorized Notes - Quotations: (arranged alphabetically by author) B-G (Box 7)
  - Uncategorized Notes - Quotations: (arranged alphabetically by author) H-R (Box 8)
  - Uncategorized Notes - Quotations: (arranged alphabetically by author) S-Z (Box 9)
- Material About Ferré, Series VI
  - Articles
    - "Ferré, unfair, uninformed." (letter to editor in unidentified periodical), No date (Box 10)
    - Fuller, David, Otis. The Blasphemies of Nels Ferré. Grand Rapids MI: Wealthy St. Baptist Church., No date (Box 10)
    - Pierce, Richard D. "Nels Fredrick Solomon Ferré." ADVANCE (January 1944): 6-7. (Box 10)
    - Bjorn, Thyra and Margaret Ferré. "A Boy Who Dared to Dream." YOUNG PEOPLE 70 (July 16, 1950): 1, 6. (2 copies) (Box 10)
    - "Redaktionens Spalt: Se Pa Klockan!" UNGA KAMRATER 10 (Mar. 5-11, 1950): 2. (Box 10)
    - Yamaka, Shiroshi. "Correspondence from America with Sketches, no. 42." MUTSU-SHIMPO 2630 (Apr. 10, 1953). (Japanese original with English translation) (Box 10)
    - Soper, David Wesley. "The Postcritical Theology of Nels F.S. Ferré." Chap. in MAJOR VOICES IN AMERICAN THEOLOGY. Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1953. pp. 73-105 (Box 10)
    - LeQuire, Louise. "Creative Art Marks Many New Churches." NASHVILLE BANNER (Sep. 16, 1954) (Box 10)
    - "What They Think."(excerpts from speech) NEWSWEEK (November 8, 1954): 65. (Box 10)
    - [incomplete article in which NFSF is quoted] CHRISTIAN LIFE (Mar.-Apr. 1956) (Box 10)
    - Hordern, William. "The Theology of Nels Ferré." THE PASTOR 19 (Feb. 1956): 10-12. (Box 10)
    - Pemberton, Prentiss L. "An Examination of Some Criticisms of Talcott Parsons' Sociology of Religion." JOURNAL OF RELIGION 36 (Oct. 1956): 241-256. (Box 10)
    - Soper, David Wesley. "The Sufficiency of God: The Postcritical Theology of Nels F.S. Ferré." BRITISH WEEKLY (Aug. 9, 1956): 9, 11. (Box 10)
    - White, S.S .. "The Controversy Between Ferré and Tillich, I." THE PREACHER'S MAGAZINE 31/9 (Sep. 1956): 1-5. (Box 10)
    - White, S.S .. "The Controversy Between Ferre and Tillich, III." THE PREACHER'S MAGAZINE 31/11 (Nov. 1956): 16-20. (Box 10)
    - How to Lecture on Theology When It's Ninety-Five in the Shade." BRITISH WEEKLY 140/3688 (July 18, 1957): 1. (9 pictures, Front Page, comments by Ed.) (Box 10)
    - Ilico. "An Unsatisfactory Conversation." 139/3673 BRITISH WEEKLY (Apr. 4, 1957): 4. (Box 10)
    - "Vespers Draws Outstanding Theologians." PEABODY REFLECTOR 30/4 (May-June 1957): 130. (Box 10)
    - Bradley, William L .. "Theology a Live Topic at Boston." ADVANCE 150/13 (July 8, 1958): 8-10. (Box 10)
    - Gray, Wallace. "Whitehead and Ferré Discuss God." THE HIBBERT JOURNAL 56/125 (Apr. 1958): 262-272. (Box 10)
    - Clark, Gordon H. "The Theology of Nels F.S. Ferré." THE SOUTHERN PRESBYTERIAN JOURNAL 17/46 (Mar. 18, 1959): 6-9. (Box 10)
    - "Dr. Nels F.S. Ferré." (editorial) OPINION (July,Aug.,Sep. 1959): 8-9. (Box 10)
    - "Graham and Ferré" THE BRITISH WEEKLY 143/3777 (Apr. 2, 1959): 6. (Box 10)
    - Gray, Wallace. "Issues in Contemporary Evangelism, I: Billy Graham Meets Nels Ferre." RELIGION IN LIFE 28/2 (Spring 1959): 163-180. (Box 10)
    - Johnson, Robert Clyde. "The Normative Theology of Nels F.S. Ferré." in AUTHORITY IN PROTESTANT THEOLOGY. ed. Robert Clyde Johnson. Philadelphia: Westminster Press, 1959. pp. 153-161. (Box 10)
    - "About the New Mood in Politics." [incomplete article in which NFSF is quoted] ESQUIRE (Jan. 1960):. (Box 10)
    - Gray, Wallace. "Billy Grahams Theologie?" MONATSCHRIFT FUR PASTORALTHEOLOGIE 49/9 (Sep. 1960): 359-371. (Box 10)
    - Gray, Wallace. "Nels Ferré and Reinhold Niebuhr Discuss War." CANADIAN JOURNAL OF THEOLOGY 6/4 (Oct. 1960): 237-261. (Box 10)
    - Nelson, Alvin F. and Gustave A. Ferré. "God as Agape." in BASIC PHILOSOPHICAL ISSUES.: Educational Publishers, 1962. pp. 321-326. (Box 10)
    - Cobb, John B. "On Being Post-Christian." CHRISTIAN ADVOCATE 7/12 (June 6, 1963): 12-13. (Box 10)
    - Dawson, John B. "Nels Ferré, Who Proved Prayer's Power." in PEOPLE OF PRAYER. Nashville: Upper Room, 1963. pp. 46-51. (Box 10)
    - Haas, Theodore E. "The Extreme Middle in Christian Theology: An Interpretation of Nels Ferré." THEOLOGY AND LIFE 6/2 (Summer 1963): 144-153. (Box 10)
    - Parrinder, E. G. "Religion Today. 16. Is the World Council in Heresy?" THE HIBBERT JOURNAL 61/243 (July 1963): 161-164. (Box 10)
    - Duthie, Charles. "The God Who Is Involved: The Theology of Nels Ferré." BRITISH WEEKLY (Dec. 2, 1965): 12-13. (Box 10)
    - Duthie, Charles. "The Problem of Evil." BRITISH WEEKLY (Dec. 9, 1965): 9. (Box 10)
    - Duthie, Charles. "The Theologian for Today: Nels Ferré." BRITISH WEEKLY (Nov. 25, 1965): 10-11. (Box 10)
    - Dean, Larry. "Dr. Ferré Delivers 1st Lecture at BYU." DAILY UNIVERSE [Brigham Young University] (Feb. 1966): 1-2 (Box 10)
    - Gray, Wallace. "God Is Dead -- Or Is He?" COMMUNIO VIATORUM 1-2 (1968): 39-60. (Box 10)
  - Reviews of NFSF books
    - Barclay, William. "Review of 'Strength to Live with God.' by Nels F.S. Ferré." THE EXPOSITORY TIMES 68 (May 1957): 255-256. (Box 10)
    - McCracken, Robert J. "Review of 'Christ and the Christian.' by Nels F.S. Ferré." WESTMINSTER BOOKMAN 17/4 (Dec. 1958) :5-6. (Box 10)
    - "Dr. Nels Ferré's 'Christ and the Christian'." THE EXPOSITORY TIMES 70/7 (Apr. 1959): 193-195. (Box 10)
    - Albritton, Walter M. "Review of 'Know Your Faith' by Nels F.S. Ferré." THE NEW CHRISTIAN ADVOCATE (Sep. 1959): 84-85. (Box 10)
    - Johnson, Robert Clyde. "Review of 'Know Your Faith' by Nels F.S. Ferré." THE WESTMINSTER BOOKMAN 18/3 (Sep. 1959): 7-8. (Box 10)
    - Luecke, Richard. "Christ and the Christian, by Nels F.S. Ferré." THEOLOGY TODAY 16/4 (Jan. 1960): 530-539. (Box 10)
    - Temple, Howard. "Notes on the Theologian's Comment on Hermeneutics." JOURNAL OF BIBLICAL LITERATURE 79/2 (1960): 164-166. (Box 10)
    - Miller, William Robert. "Review of 'God's New Age' and 'The Finality of Faith.' by Nels F.S. Ferré." FELLOWSHIP 29/17 (Sep. 1, 1963): 28-29. (Box 10)
    - Homrighausen, E.G. "Review of 'A Theology for Christian Education.' by Nels F.S. Ferré." RELIGIOUS EDUCATION 62 (Nov.-Dec. 1967): 528-530. (Box 10)
    - Rood, Wayne R. "Review of 'A Theology for Christian Education.' by Nels F.S. Ferré." RELIGION IN LIFE 36/4 (Winter 1967): 617-619. (Box 10)
    - Cobb, W. Daniel. "Review of 'The Living God of Nowhere and Nothing. I by Nels F.S. Ferre." ENCOUNTER 29/2 (Spring 1968): 218-219. (Box 10)
    - Tait, Gordon L. "The Universal Word and Its Author." WOOSTER ALUMNI MAGAZINE 84/1 (Oct. 1969): 10-12. (Box 10)
    - Durfee, Harold A. "Review of 'The Universal Word.' by Nels F.S. Ferre." RELIGION IN LIFE 39/1 (Spring 1970): 148-149. (Box 10)
  - Dissertations on NFSF
    - Schrag, Oswald O. EXISTENTIALISM AND RATIONALISM IN THE THOUGHT OF NELS F. S. FERRE. Boston: Boston University Graduate School, 1952 (Box 10)
    - Moissides, George Lazarus. EDUCATIONAL IMPLICATIONS OF THE THEOLOGY OF HENRY NELSON WEIMAN AND OF THE THEOLOGY OF NELS F. S. FERRE. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University, Graduate School of Education, 1955 (Box 10)
    - Molloy, Vincent P. THE CHRISTOLOGY OF NELS F. S. FERRE. Rome: Catholic Book Agency, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Chandler, George Patterson. THE ORIGINS AND DEVELOPMENT OF THEOLOGICAL METHOD IN NELS FERRE. Atlanta: Emory University Graduate School, 1967 (Box 10)
  - Unpublished papers on NFSF
    - Robert Brank Fulton, "Towards a fuller inter-faith dialogue.", No date, after 1967 (Box 10)
  - Autobiographical
    - Typescript autobiography: "Naked Before God: A Saga of Faith", No date (Box 11)